<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Fish Tank on Syntactic Sugar</title>
    <link>https://adelehedrick.github.io/tags/fish-tank/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Fish Tank on Syntactic Sugar</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://adelehedrick.github.io/tags/fish-tank/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Cleaning a Used Fish Tank</title>
      <link>https://adelehedrick.github.io/blog/2017/01/03/cleaning-used-tank/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adelehedrick.github.io/blog/2017/01/03/cleaning-used-tank/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;getting-a-deal-on-varagesale&#34;&gt;Getting a Deal On Varagesale&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this aquaponics system, I am using an ancient microwave stand to support the whole system (trying to limit costs in some areas so I can splurge in others), and so I am restricted to a 10 gallon fish tank. Since I am trying to save money building this system, I decided to buy a used tank, and found the perfect sized tank for $10 CAD on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.varagesale.com/&#34;&gt;Varagesale&lt;/a&gt; from a person that lives within 5 km from me! The kind fellow included all the accessories that goes into keeping fish (filter, heater, lid and light), but I do not intend on using anything except for the tank itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../img/aquaponics/first-10-gal-system/cleaning-tank-before.jpg&#34; width=&#34;400px&#34; alt=&#34;Cleaning Used Tank - Before&#34; &gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see the tank is pretty grungy and has calcium/lime/algae/aliens left over on it. The struggle with this task is that whatever you use to clean the tank has to be safe to eat as well as safe for fish and plants to survive with. Therefore, I got to use the extreme cleaning power of &lt;em&gt;vinegar&lt;/em&gt;, followed by an extreme rinse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;cleaning-materials&#34;&gt;Cleaning Materials&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Toothbrush&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Razor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vinegar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 year old (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;cleaning-method&#34;&gt;Cleaning Method&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put, I dipped the toothbrush in straight up vinegar and scrubbed the areas of extreme build up, scrapped the build up with the razor, and then scrub with the toothbrush yet again. Once I felt  satisfied with the results, I added a couple jugs worth of tap water to rinse off the sides and use a paper towel to continue washing the inside of the tank. When I emptied the vinegar water (assisted by my strong man husband), I continued to rinse the inside of the tank till I was satisfied the vinegar was all gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../img/aquaponics/first-10-gal-system/cleaning-tank-after.jpg&#34; width=&#34;400px&#34; alt=&#34;Cleaning Used Tank - After&#34; &gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;result&#34;&gt;Result&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see in the above picture (still has vinegar/water in the tank) the results were amazing! Considering I got this tank for $10 CAD, I would call this a win!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will see how my rinsing job holds up when I add water and start observing the pH.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>